Note: The following is base on my own observations, as well as trials and errors.

Steps of how I decrypt an encrypted message using matrices with unknown NxN square matrix, 
which is the key, and only given the last 4 characters of the original message, 
assuming the message is > 4 characters in length.


e.g.

encrypted message using 2x2:

21  −8  −10  15  −13  13  10  −5  25  −5  19  −5  6  1  40  −20  21  −3  28  −14

decrypt using a 2x2 matrix... Last characters are RON_ ('_' for space).




Step 1: Find the key NxN matrix, size varies, in this case 2x2.
     
1.1: write this down for reference 

Matrix of the last four encoded characters
   ▲       Matrix of the last four unencoded characters equivalent of the encoded version
   |          ▲          
   |          |        We need to find this NxN key Matrix
   |          |             ▲
[21  -3]   [18 15] 	    |
|      | = |	 | * [unknown NxN key Matrix]
[28 -14]   [14  0]



Step 2: Find the inverse of the matrix containing unencoded characters

    [18 15]   [0     1/14]
inv |     | = |          |
    [14  0]   [1/15 -3/35]

Step 3: multiply both sides of the equation from step 1.1 with the inverse you found from step 2. 

Note: Make sure that on the right side you multiply the inverse matrix with the unencoded matrix and NOT with the unknown NxN key matrix.
Note: Make sure that the inverse matrix is on the left side of the matrices containing the encoded and unencoded characters.
      Doing so will give you an Identity matrix on the right side which we can ignore since multiplying any matrix with an
      Identity matrix gives the same matrix, and on the left side the unknown NxN key matrix we are looking for.

Visually it would looked the below diagram:

			Matrix of the last four encoded characters
		   	▲    	      Matrix of the last four unencoded characters equivalent of the encoded version
Inverse from step 2	|    	   	     ▲                            
    ▲		  	|     		     |	                                  
    |		   |----|     		     |            We need to find this NxN key Matrix           
    |              |          		     |               ▲            
[0     1/14]	[21  -3]   [0     1/14]	  [18 15]            |          
|	   | *	|      | = |	      |	* |	| * [unknown NxN key Matrix]	
[1/15 -3/35]	[28 -14]   [1/15 -3/35]	  [14  0]   
    |                           |
    |                           ▼
    |                        This can be on the right or left side of the unencoded matrix after distribution, the result will always be an Identity matrix.
    |			     However, I recommend distributing it on the left side of the unencoded matrix to be consistent with the left side of the equation.
    |
    ▼
  On the left side of the encoded matrix
  Again, make sure this is on the left side of the encoded matrix when you multiply 
  and not on the right side of the encoded matrix. Else, you'll get the wrong NxN unknown key


RESULT after step 3: The key for decrypting the encrypted message.




step 5: Find the inverse of the key found on step 2.

Step 6: partition the remaining encrypted message into 1xN or NxN(same size of the key matrix, as long as we can multiply it with the inverse matrix of the key found on step 5.

Note: Make sure to partition this is order! This ensure the characters are decoded in the order it was originally written by the sender.

e.g.

Original encoded message:

21  −8  −10  15  −13  13  10  −5  25  −5  19  −5  6  1  40  −20  21  −3  28  −14

Partitioned into 1x2 because this allows us to multiply with the inverse matrix of key

[21 -8] [-10 15] [-13 13] [10 -5] [25 -5] [19 -5] [6 1] [40 -20] 

[21 -3] [28 -14] is already known so no need to find this two groups.


OR


Partitioned into 2x2 because this is the size of the key matrix and it allows us to multiply with the inverse matrix of key.

[21  -8]   [-13 13]   [25 -5]   [6    1]
|      |   |      |   |     |   |      |
[-10 15]   [10  -5]   [19 -5]   [40 -20]


Note: If ever there's a left over after partitioning just add numbers of same encoded given to allow multiplication with the inverse matrix.



Step 7: Multiply each partition with the inverse of the key found on step 4

Note: The order on which you multiply matters! Make sure the partition is on the left side and the inverse matrix of key on the right side.

e.g.

[21  -8]
|      | * [inverse matrix of key found on step 5]
[-10 15]


RESULT after step 7: decoded characters




Step 8: Repeat for all partitons until you run out.



DONE!

YAY!



